Ida Langdon Papers, 1899-1962
Elmira College
Ida Langdon Papers, 1899-1962
The Ida Langdon Papers contain an assortment of teaching and lecture materials from her early tenure as a professor of English Literature at Elmira College, including collegiate materials from her matriculation at Bryn Mawr College. The collection also includes materials from Dr. Lane Cooper, a professor at Cornell University where Langdon received her Doctorate and various letters of correspondence and newspaper clippings. Items concerning her association with her uncle, Mark Twain, are at a minimum.
1.31 linear ft.
Langdon, Ida
Elmira College
Unrestricted.
Ida Langdon was born in Elmira, New York to parents Charles J. Langdon and Ida Clark Langdon. She was educated at Bryn Mawr College and completed her graduate and doctorate degrees in English from Cornell University.
Langdon taught at Bryn Mawr College and Wellesley before returning home to Elmira to care for her ailing mother. Joining the English department in 1920, Langdon went on to teach over 20 years at the institution. She became a professor Emeritus at the institution in 1945.
Langdon was the niece of Samuel Langhorne Clemens, better known as Mark Twain, whom married her aunt, Olivia Langdon. Ida spent a number of summers at Quarry Farm with the Clemens’ family. Her association with the famous author was well-known in Elmira.
Ida Langdon died in 1964 at the age of 83.
Langdon, Ida; Cooper, Lane; Elmira College; Bryn Mawr College; Authors; Women college teachers; Manuscripts; Letters; Postcards; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Books; Notebooks; Photographs
The Ida Langdon Papers contain an assortment of teaching and lecture materials from her tenure as a professor of English Literature at Elmira College. The collection also includes collegiate materials from her matriculation at Bryn Mawr College, materials from Dr. Lane Cooper, a professor at Cornell University where Langdon received her Masters and Doctorate degrees, various letters of correspondence and newspaper clippings.
The bulk of the collection contains manuscript writings for class lectures at Elmira College. There are a number of published items collected by Langdon concerning Dr. Lane Cooper of Cornell. The majority of the original materials in the collection are from Langdon’s professional career at Bryn Mawr in 1913 and her early career at Elmira College in the 1920’s.
The collection contains one folder of news clipping about Langdon’s uncle, Mark Twain.
Organization Note:
The Ida Langdon Papers have been organized into the following series:
Series 1: Teaching and Lecture Materials [1913-1954, undated]
Series 2: Dr. Lane Cooper Materials [1909-1962, undated]
Series 3: Miscellaneous Materials [1899-1951]
- SERIES 1: TEACHING AND LECTURE MATERIALS [1913-1954, undated], SERIES NOTE: The series contains various manuscripts and lectures, including clippings, notes and a number of notebooks from her tenure as a faculty member at Bryn Mawr. The series is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Bryn Mawr -- Loose notes - first year English [undated], 1899-1962 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Bryn Mawr -- English, Notebook and notes [1913-1915] (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Bryn Mawr -- First Year Composition Notebook [1913-1914] (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Bryn Mawr -- First Year Composition Notebook, February [1915] (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Bryn Mawr -- First Year Composition Notebook [1914-1915] (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Bryn Mawr -- Second Year Composition Notebook [1914-1915] (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Bryn Mawr -- First Year Composition Notebook [1915-1916] (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Lecture -- "Dante as a poet" -- edited typescript [undated], 1899-1962 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Lecture -- "Early nineteenth century poets" [undated], 1899-1962 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Lecture -- "The English and Scotch Ballads" typescript [undated], 1899-1962 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Lecture -- "the Habit and art of reading" edited typescript [undated], 1899-1962 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Lecture -- "The Isle of Iona," Chapel Talk, Feb. 1928 [1928] (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Lecture -- "Modern Poetry" to the AAUW [undated], 1899-1962 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Lecture -- "Poetry as an art," Lecture I [1927] (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Lecture -- "Poetry as an art,"Lecture II [1927] (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Lecture -- "Some impressions of Ireland", Nov. 13, 1928 [1928] (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Lecture -- "Some personal experiences of Ireland," -- Handwritten on notecards, September 1932 [1932] (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Lecture -- "The Sonnet" -- edited typescript [undated], 1899-1962 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Lecture for the Garden Club [undated], 1899-1962 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Notes -- periods of English literature [undated], 1899-1962 (Box-folder 1: 20)
- SERIES 2: LANE COOPER MATERIALS [1909-1962, undated], SERIES NOTE: This series contains correspondence and a collection of publications from Lane Cooper, a professor at Cornell University. The series is organized alphabetically by folder title.
  - Correspondence -- Letters to Ida from Lane Cooper [1921-1954] (Box-folder 2 1)
  - Correspondence -- Regarding Lane Cooper [1913-1962] (Box-folder 2 2)
  - The Lane Cooper Fund -- Book [undated], 1899-1962 (Box-folder 2 3)
  - Lane Cooper Publications -- items inscribed to Ida (incl. Note from Ida attached to 1925 School and Society) [1917-1948] (Box-folder 2 4)
  - Lane Cooper Publications -- items inscribed to Ida [1909-1917] (Box-folder 2 5)
  - Lane Cooper Publications -- Reviews [1910-1959, undated] (Box-folder 2 6)
  - Mark Twain's Lilacs and Laburnams from Quarry Farm [1932] (Box-folder 2 7)
- SERIES 3: MISCELLANEOUS MATERIALS, 1899 - 1962; SERIES NOTE: This series contains correspondence, Langdon’s college notebooks, and various other publications and English materials collected by Ida Langdon. The series is arranged alphabetically by folder title
  - Bryn Mawr -- English Literature, Langdon college notebook [1899] (Box-folder 3 1)
  - Bryn Mawr -- English Literature II, Langdon college notebook [1899] (Box-folder 3 2)
  - Clippings - Concerning works on Shakespeare [1923, undated] (Box-folder 3 3)
  - Clippings-- Lectures (obit. Joseph Adams) [undated], 1899-1962 (Box-folder 3 4)
  - Clippings - Non-Communicative Art by Max Eastman [1954] (Box-folder 3 5)
  - Clippings: Miscellaneous -- Obit. Walter Bullock, James Thompson's Library, Henry James Last Home, Henry Adams [1925, undated] (Box-folder 3 6)
  - Chambers, R. W. -- Correspondence and Chambers publications publication [1925-1951, undated] (Box-folder 3 7)
  - Florence, Italy -- "Handbook of Florence and its Environs" [1890] (Box-folder 3 8)
  - Floyd, Carlisle -- Playbills [1956-1959] (Box-folder 3 9)
  - Marsden, Mal -- Letter from Ida [1962] (Box-folder 3 10)
  - Nevin, Margaret - Margaret Nevin [1928-1964] (Box-folder 3 11)
  - Palmer, Georgianna -- photocopied article [undated], 1899-1962 (Box-folder 3 12)
  - "Peake" -- Letter from Codner, England [1914?] (Box-folder 3 13)
  - Ramsey, Paul, Mrs. -- Letter from Ida [1963] (Box-folder 3 14)
  - Dr. Stuart -- Card with poem, Elmira. [undated], 1899-1962 (Box-folder 3 15)
  - Tell, Wilhelm - German [1904] (Box-folder 3 16)
  - Various clippings -- Includes items on Mark Twain [1882-1962] (Box-folder 3 17)
  - Various miscellaneous materials - Card with John Muir quote, Cornell Studies in English class list, war map of Europe, photograph [undated], 1882 - 1962 (Box-folder 3 18)